Section 3.2 Definitions how we define
problems directly impacts
which strategies we pursue in solving that
problem. In
a new and evolving field like AI safety,
clearly
defined terms are essential for effective
communication and research.
Ambiguity leads to miscommunication,
hinders collaboration, obscures
disagreements, and
facilitates safety. Washington the terms
we use reflect our
assumptions about the nature of the
problems we're trying
to solve and shape the solutions we
develop. Terms
like alignment and safety are used with
varying meanings,
reflecting different underlying
assumptions about the nature of the
problem and the research goals. The goal
of this
section is to explain different
perspectives on these words,
what specific safety strategies aim to
achieve, and establish
how our text will utilize them. AI Safety
Here
is a definition of AI ensuring that AI
systems
do not inadvertently or deliberately cause
harm or danger
to humans or the environment through
research that identifies
causes of unintended AI behavior and
develops tools for
safe and reliable operation. AI safety
ensures AI systems
do not cause harm to humans or the
environment.
It encompasses the broadest range of
research and engineering
practices focused on preventing harmful
outcomes from AI systems.
While alignment focuses on aspects such as
an AI's
goals and intentions, safety addresses a
broader range of
concerns. It is concerned with ensuring
that AI systems
do not inadvertently or deliberately cause
harm or danger
to humans or the environment. AI safety
research seeks
to identify the causes of unintended AI
behavior and
develop tools for ensuring safe and
reliable operation. It
can include technical subfields like
robustness ensuring reliable performance,
including against adversarial attacks
Monitoring observing AI behavior and
capability control limiting potentially
dangerous abilities AI Alignment the
term AI alignment refers to the the
problem of
building machines that faithfully try to
do what we
want them to do or what we ought to
want them to do. AI alignment aims to
ensure
AI systems act in accordance with human
intentions and
values. Alignment is a subset of safety
that focuses
specifically on the technical problem of
ensuring AI objectives
align human intentions and values.
Theoretically, a system could
be aligned but unsafe, for example
Competently pursuing the
wrong goal due to misspecification or safe
but unaligned,
for example constrained by control
mechanisms despite misaligned objectives.
While this sounds straightforward, the
precise scope varies significantly
across research communities, but we
already saw a brief
definition of alignment in the previous
chapter, but this
section offers a more nuanced perspective
on the various
definitions that we could potentially work
with. The textbook
has a supplementary note titled what Do We
Mean
by Alignment? Which we'll skip. Let's
define AI ethics,
the study and application of moral
principles to AI
development and deployment, addressing
questions of fairness, transparency,
accountability,
privacy, autonomy, and other human values
that AI systems
should respect or promote. AI ethics is
the field
that examines the moral principles and
societal implications of
AI systems. It addresses the ethical
considerations of potential
societal upheavals resulting from AI
advancements and the moral
frameworks necessary to navigate these
changes. The core of
AI ethics lies in ensuring that AI
developments are
aligned with human dignity, fairness, and
societal well being
through a deep understanding of their
broader societal impact.
Research in AI ethics would encompass, for
example, privacy
norms. Identifying and mitigating bias in
systems ethics complements
technical safety approaches by providing
normative guidance on what
constitutes beneficial AI outcomes.
Alignment focuses on ensuring AI
systems pursue intended objectives.
Research in ethics focuses on
which objectives are worth pursuing. AI
ethics might also
include discussions of digital rights and
potentially even the
rights of digital minds and AIs in the
future.
This chapter focuses primarily on safety
frameworks as they
inform technical, safety, and governance
strategies rather than exploring
ethics, meta ethics, or digital rights.
Section. AI Control
we define AI control as follows. The
technical and
procedural measures designed to prevent AI
systems from causing
unacceptable outcomes, even if these
systems actively attempt to
subvert safety measures. Control focuses
on maintaining human oversight
regardless of whether the AI's objectives
align with human
intentions. AI control ensures systems
remain under human authority
despite potential misalignment. AI control
implements mechanisms such as
to ensure AI systems remain under human
direction even
when they might act against our interests.
Unlike alignment
approaches that focus on giving AI systems
the right
goals, control addresses what happens if
those goals diverge
from human intentions. Control and
alignment work as complementary
safety approaches, while alignment aims to
prevent preference divergence.
By designing systems with the right
objectives, control creates
layers of security that function even when
alignment fails.
Control measures include monitoring AI
actions, restricting system capabilities,
human auditing processes, and mechanisms
to terminate AI systems
when necessary. Some researchers argue
that even if alignment
is needed for superintelligence level AIs,
control through monitoring
may be a working strategy for less capable
systems.
Ideally, an AGI would be aligned and
controllable, meaning
it would have the right goals and be
subject
to human oversight and intervention if
something goes wrong.
The control line of AI safety work is
discussed
in much more detail in our chapter on AI
evaluations.